[Music]
all right
hello everyone thanks for joining
actinflab live stream number 41.1
it's april 6 2022.
welcome to the actin flap we're a
participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference
this is a recorded and an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve on our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome here and we'll be following good
video etiquette for livestream
if you want to learn more about any
actinflab activities head over to
activeinference.org
and you can learn more there
all right today in
stream number 41.1 we are continuing to
learn and discuss the paper
extended active inference
constructing predictive cognition beyond
skulls by constant clark kirchoff and
fristen from 2020
and
today in the dot one we're going to have
some introductions
revisit the road map and some of the big
questions of the paper
and then we can have an open discussion
around the figures formalism anything
else that people think is relevant and
for those who are watching live feel
free to add any questions or comments in
the live chat
so we can start just by saying hello um
hearing perhaps blue's first thoughts on
uh the paper and from dean and i we can
revisit
what we've been thinking about
potentially since the dot zero which
i'll save for soon so i'm daniel i'm a
researcher in california and i'll pass
it to d
thanks daniel i'm dean i'm up here in
calgary i'm a little nasally today
because i'm fighting off a bit of a cold
um what i've been thinking about since
we
did the dot zero is the
sort of the
the idea around how cognition is maybe
cultural
and i'll just leave it at that because
maybe we can have a bit of a
conversation about that today i'll pass
it to blue
hi i'm blue i'm an independent research
consultant in new mexico
and i um yeah okay so i'll give some
first thoughts on the paper
um one thing that really stuck out to me
was um the idea of glue and truth
so
um that like gave a whole new like level
like so so in order for you to have like
extended cognition
you have to believe in it and you have
to
you have to be glued to it like you have
to have access to it whenever you need
it and you have to believe that it's
valid right so that that's the glue and
truth idea that they unpacked in the
paper and um
it gave like a whole new
meaning of like being glued to your
phone to me like i was like oh this is
why we're always glued to our phone
there's glue and there's truth right um
so that was kind of interesting and then
um definitely like
uh to touch on what dean was saying i
think that
the cognition and betting in culture is
a super interesting aspect and like in
the very last section of the paper they
were talking about like the ability to
give like theater like plays without
being able to rehearse just based on
cultural cues and knowing the context
and just being so well versed and how to
cue off of each other or um this kind of
thing and it reminded me like of maybe
like a jazz improv like we know like
what's acceptable or like when you're
playing when you have like a jam band
and you're playing all the time like you
kind of just
know where to pick off or or you know
daniel and i are constantly leaving
stigmatic traces like like there's like
this extended cognition that i see
happen like we'll both be doing the same
thing at the same time like i was just
doing that like uh it's hard to
eliminate redundancy um in those kinds
of circumstances so so there is like the
shared culture and how like
central like even because culture yes we
have culture as a human society but like
within the elizabethan theater companies
there's their own culture right of
i don't know how many people were in the
theater company 20. so so like there's
that and being able to cue off of each
other and like you know the active
inference lab which is growing every day
um reach out if you haven't yet signed
up to be a participant
um
so like within the active inference lab
like where we have our community and we
have like you know some people we
interact with on a very regular basis
and then others less so and so we're
kind of able to cue off of each other in
that kind of way and so
how does this go out to like your
religious culture
your
state culture like your country culture
like let alone society at large so so
this idea of cultural
cognition i think is very um
like salient uh
and also like
really um speaks to the iq tests or not
not iq tests but even like childhood
development and learning like in some
cultures when you give a child you know
some pieces and do a demonstration for
them of how to like you know stack
blocks together or how to like make a
lego thing um in some cultures like i
mean especially in the west we see like
a child who assembles the blocks like
maybe starts off how the demonstration
happened but then like does some new
innovative stuff like we see a child
like that oh that's so like creative and
what an ingenious way to use these you
know tools in a novel way but in some
cultures like that child must be an
idiot why isn't he just replicating like
what the adults showed him how to do um
and that's a legit like cultural
phenomenon that speaks to intelligence
and um yeah okay sorry i rambled enough
you've got my thoughts
awesome well
at least we know there'll be a lot to
jump
into
let's uh
return to the big question so for more
background of course people can
read the paper or check out the dot zero
but let's just pick up with the big
question and then the road map and then
we'll kind of jump into the more
unstructured slides
as we
framed it here the question of this
paper about extended cognition is about
how cognition is extended
and the way that the authors approach
that is this perspective of the
cognitive niche which they develop from
the perspectives that are focused on
here in this paper with this dialectic
of the cognitive niche consisting of a
psychological habit
from ecological psychology one can think
of as well as a functional behav a habit
like a neuro-behavioral habit and they
also have a selective
ecological evolutionary perspective on
the cognitive niche that axial constant
and others have developed in other work
but in this paper they were focused
mostly on um the psychological and the
functional and the time scale of
behavioral ecology rather than
evolutionary ecology but this is all
kind of in the background so they focus
on the psychological and functional
dimensions of the cognitive niche
and use that to sort of navigate and
triangulate
cognitive extensions so any other ways
to think about it or just what did other
people think of were just like a big
question that would
maybe mention active inference or not
but what is the kind of question that
leads somebody to want to read this
paper and understand what they're
conveying
yeah
i think one of the interesting things
here is that if you
encounter something that you don't
believe is an extension or a
continuation of the prior culture
so you're walking into a new habitat
we'll just call it that
what what does that then imply in terms
of your ability to cognit
as a newbie cogni cognitively extend
into that situation
i think that's what this paper is really
interesting uh in terms of discussing
because
not so long ago there were a couple of
um researchers writers glave and wagner
who talked about um experiential
learning and how you could be on the
periphery
of a of a culture
and you would slowly move your way
closer and closer to whatever the core
of that culture is this doesn't speak to
the
the cultural aspects of cognitive
extension in that way
so
my question is
when you when you walk into a new
culture or something that you don't feel
that you're necessarily
um familiar with
how does how does your
cognitive extension get taken up in that
new culture
yes as opposed to opposed to the
participants in the culture right
there's there's two components to this
it's how the people will treat you for
example but it's how the culture treats
you as well so there's two parts to that
and i just i think that's really
interesting they haven't broken it out
in this paper per se
but they certainly lead to that kind of
question because of the
the research and the argument that
they've been able to put forward
nice um
three researchers walk into a new habit
is it a psychological habit is it a
functional habit and then that makes me
think about like the culture of a music
festival or something when you're at the
periphery there's people who are just
joining like you are or people who are
leaving or people who want a little bit
of a space away from the main action but
using that sort of inner and outer
culture idea
very interesting yep
so
the idea of being like a newcomer is
pretty interesting in in this context
because there has to be some kind of
reciprocity
um
that like you are
expecting the niche to be a certain way
or maybe you learn the ways of the niche
you don't really have an expectation or
you know like how your old niche was and
you carry that forward with some
prediction but as the niche is updating
you you are also updating the niche and
so as the culture is updating you
singular you yeah um you are also
updating the culture and it goes around
and around like that and i think um
or or i wonder
what
degree we all
update our culture like what is the
single characteristic maybe it's like a
big five personality trait or maybe it's
a
you know some kind of enneagram type or
maybe there's a single
dominating
thing that makes you have a strong
influence on
the culture around you or is it just
like the rate at which you transmit
information or the number of people that
you transmit information to i mean we
all know that like those nodes that are
hot spots in like you know social
networks are you know like they're the
influential nodes that have the billions
of connections
um so is it just the number of
connections that you have the level of
information that you transmit or the
quantity of information that you
transmit or or is there something like
some personality trait that actually
gives you
the ability to update your culture more
influentially than others
one last quick one last quick point i
want to kind of build on blue's point
there
so part of this and i and i'm i'm using
terminology that's not part of the paper
but i think
we could look at in cult and culturation
as a kind of a form of domestic domestic
would you domesticate
right
and so i'm not sure when a person walks
into a new culture
whether they're perceived as sort of
non-domesticated and then we're going to
get them caught up or brought up to
speed in terms of what the culture is
and i agree with you blue it is a
circular thing
i just wonder where there's a certain
amount of wildness that's brought in
when somebody new
is sort of thrown into the
the bigger cultural
pot and whether there's an effort to try
to bring them to be more influential on
the on the one than the one being
influential on the many so i always
always i'm always curious about those
things and i don't think that this is
going to get answered right now but i
think that's an important point to sort
of remember especially when we get into
the flipping part here which i can see
daniel's already got the
graph up so let's go there
we will come there
it just made me think about when the
niche is um not other people so going on
a walk through the forest and the niche
is going to be like other
trees or just the path itself
um
this kind of figure two representation
where there's an active process by which
not just is the entity doing action
selection with respect to the niche but
the niche is basically being agentified
and it is taking some sort of active
process by which it is doing an
inference on the entity and in the
forest it's like whoa are the trees
alive you know is this lord of the rings
but if this is another group of people
and this is your social niche and your
psychological and functional habitat is
other people
then it is like quite literal this could
be two people in conversation or this
could be one versus multiple and so in
the social and cognitive and cultural
niche
it is like less of a um
leap to talk about how there's cognitive
processes on both sides but then that
helps us recognize that actually it is a
continuum it's like okay so if we can
very clearly see how in the conversation
there's this optimization happening on
both sides then what does that look like
when we're in the forest okay cool so
some of those big questions have been
raised and then let's just
revise the road map
and see where they went on their little
forest journey and then we'll jump back
into the slides and um
the go from there
so they introduced the cognitive niche
active inference and extended mind
concepts
and then discussed the argument that
they're going to lead us down
and the way in which active inference
plays into it
as we mentioned just recently
they're focusing on the functional and
psychological aspects of the cognitive
niche
leaving for later that eco-evolutionary
perspective
and they're using active inference as an
integrative framework and set of
formalisms to help address that they
go through cognitive psychological and
functional niches provide a case study
with earthworms
and have several figures that we spent a
lot of time in the dot zero looking at
where in figure 1 there was somewhat of
an active entity in a niche
that could have its own dynamics but
then figure 2
introduced the idea that the niche is
also doing something like what the
entity is doing but with a symmetry so
same same but different
and then
after that discussion they
take the full turn towards extended
active inference eai and they recognize
well if the
niche or whatever is on the other side
of the entity in the way that we're
modeling it is doing something cognitive
is that a way in which we can recognize
boundaries and interfaces as well as
distributed or extended cognitive
processes
they approach that from a few different
angles like extension through space
spatial extension as well as extension
through time temporal extension
related to diachronic cognition through
time
and then they also discussed a few
pieces uh related to for example
epistemic actions
and the relevance of how
distributed cognitive systems use
epistemic actions for example knowing
where to look to find some piece of
information in the niche
that's kind of how they went through
this paper any comments on the roadmap
or we can now turn to the blank slides
don't forget about the spiced food
because that was also part of the case
case study
what about it
um i mean that was like there was the
earthworm case but then there was also
like the case of um spicing food as like
a cultural practice and um
how like potentially i mean even the act
of cooking food or how we prepare food
overall like some parts of food are
poisonous or like i mean you're gonna
eat blow fish like that's a very precise
very
mentor mentee transmitted practice
so but but i mean more than that just
also like the spices that we use can
sometimes be like
you know poisonous agents and they're
slightly toxic to us but not in small
amounts and but they also like help to
get rid of any parasites that might be
residing in the meat that we're eating
um but yeah they use that as a as a case
study also not just the earthworm with
the kidney
this is a book that we've been reading
at home recently
much depends on dinner it's kind of in
the culinary writing genre not something
we talk about too much directly here but
it's a very
interesting approach that really does
some deep dives on what we could see
from our actin flab vantage point of
like extended and encultured cognitive
processes and thinking about how food
gets to the table in all of the ways
that it gets the table how do people get
to the table how do we show up and
how does that differ through time so
it's kind of a cool book
similarly like the omnivore's dilemma
which i just read was also like how does
your food get to the table where does it
come from and yeah that's a whole
there's a whole set of practices and
like not only that but it's actually um
i mean you go back to thinking about
survival and thinking like a state uh
thinking about thinking like a state
there's a whole set of practices that
actually
construct our society based on the way
that we get food which is really um
pretty remarkable
it's a distributed metabolism with
bringing resources and nutrients
to and from
and um so it is very
related
okay so here's a few of the options
people can um take a quick little vote
or state their preference we can talk
about walking into new cognitive niches
talk a little bit about glue and truth
in the context of extended cognitive
processes and culture
about applying extended active inference
and how that is uh modeled
in its deployment as well as maybe from
a experiential
perspective what does it feel like to be
applying active inference in the
extended way
we have the question from
dave
about uh thinking about partitions
and there's a few other ways we could go
any preferences from these
so when we talk about applying active
inference are we talking about this from
a
realist or instrumentalist perspective i
just need to know
determines my vote
i think you've already said enough what
would it um mean
why does it matter
about realism and instrumentalism if
we're talking about applying extended
active inference like what are those as
you're seeing it now and what would the
um realism flavor or instrumentalist
flavor look like
well are we talking about actually what
is it like to apply active inference in
an extended way like what is that
actually like it takes on a very realist
flavor
when we're thinking about extending
active inference beyond our own
skull
or are we modeling
what are we actually doing here are we
modeling collective cognition collective
predictive processing
as extended active inference or what are
we actually doing here um i i would like
to know what you guys think
yes dean
my
curiosity around this is always
to do with things that have actually
happened but i still think there's a
sort of a
an inter a tool or instrumentalist part
around two when i first joined this
community
i don't know that i could have gotten
become part of whatever the community is
evolving into
without having both a kind of a realism
perspective and an instrumentalism
perspective so
i'm kind of i'm always kind of curious
when people want to break it out into
those two things i'm a minimum of two
thing guy
i think both of them both of them exist
and i don't think we can actually do
anything without having both of them so
let's say we drop one of the other blue
what happens in terms of our ability to
sort of get a real grip on or optimize
or do any of the things that we want to
do in terms of becoming enculturated
like if we drop one of the two
and just put all of our our our
resources in the other
domain
does like do we do that
naturally or do we do that in in those
domesticated situations right if we're
doing it in the wild
if we're truly having to go out there
and forage don't we use both that's my
question
so i will respond to that
um
i do think
we use both i think
i drop the instrumentalist perspective
all the time
like
i drop it when i think about
extending my cognition into my niche
environment and and i think about
extending my cognition into my group of
active inference people or or whatever i
drop the instrumentalist perspective
frequently in language in thought like i
think about oh what is it like to
actively infer xyz
but i never
lose sight of
the instrumentalist perspective as the
real way things are
right does that make sense like so the
instrumentalist perspective is the real
way things are like this is a tool i
talk about it as if it's not i think
about it as if it's not but
essentially
in my generative model like from the
realist perspective in my model when i
talk about my model i am modeling my
model and i'm doing it with the
instrument of active inference
yeah well again that's that's where i
find this really interesting if we're
going to extend extend
it's hard enough to
to talk about
building a niche or constructing a niche
without tools
or without realism
but if you're going to do that as an
extended cognition exercise now it's
even more complicated even more complex
how do you drop one of the two
and and and continue to feel like you're
you're accomplishing something
i i don't i don't want to get into
debate well i don't think we're getting
into debates about it's one or the other
but i think when you're trying to figure
things out
to just say okay i'm gonna i'm
automatically gonna blind one eye
just because i want the other eye to
grow bigger the other eye doesn't grow
bigger so
why are you doing that to yourself
that's what i always ask
so we can um
think about applying extended active
imprints
and as blue initially asked are we
approaching this
in what ways from a realism in what ways
from an instrumentalism perspective so
the realist question
just we're at the dmv right getting our
driver's license renewed
and they ask us to cover one of our eyes
because they actually do want to
understand that one of the eyes has a
certain visual capacity so we're closing
the instrumentalism eye and it's like to
the extent that we can even talk about
the real
cognitive systems actually really
do have functional dependencies that
extend beyond any actual boundary in the
world or that we state so however many
philosophical caveats you need to add
about realism
this eye
has no problem seeing
that
the functional components of cognition
are distributed so that is realism or
really extended active inference so
r e a
i
the instrumentalism i
is how are we going to
utilize actin
in a way that is useful and so
here with this eye we can see that
no matter what we're going to have to
model along with compromises like
accuracy minus complexity
the ways in which
our models of the cognitive systems they
actually do
require in the model the as-if influence
of influences beyond their neural system
so whether those influences beyond
the actual boundaries are real or
whether those influences beyond the
statistical boundaries are statistically
real
we can oscillate and like look at
something because we're the one who's
generating those
visuals and integrating those
perspectives into like a single coherent
generative model
and um one last on this a lot of times
somebody will think well what does a bug
see what does an insect see and it has
like a thousand different views of the
world
but of course we have two eyes and see
just one vision of the world so
there's reason to think that no matter
how many
facets of the insect i there are
they're still having just a single
coherent visual generative model
so maybe there's even other perspectives
but
that
won't mean that we are
not having a singular underlying
coherent generative experience so
okay
that
um
bridge being crossed or burnt depending
on what you think
what are some situations where we would
be applying extended active inference
so and also to distinguish that question
from just like where would we want to be
extending active inference
where would specifically
extended perspectives on active
inference be really important as opposed
to just
non-extended and maybe it'd be helpful
there to look at figure one and two just
to remind ourselves of those differences
so think about the examples while we yes
blue first go for it
um
so
in the spirit of active inference being
a scale-free framework like i think
about extended active inference as
very critical
to
this skill friendly slash skill-free
way that we think about active inference
just because as a biological system
were layers and layers and layers and
layers and layers deep so like
i this like
whatever my ego perceives as me blue
i am an embodied
image of extended active inference i
mean so so i don't see it happening
anywhere i don't see it extended active
inference not happening anywhere like i
see what happens in my skull a function
as of what's happening in my cells and
my tissues and my organs etc
because all of those subunits of blue
are
doing this extended active inference
with one another
um but if we want to look specifically
at like a group
function
um which which may be necessary or or
maybe not i mean to go beyond our skull
are we looking at like how organizations
function uh which maybe dean
wants to talk about more or how you know
states function or how
institutions function at large um so so
do we have to get actually beyond the
physical body to go beyond our skull or
can we go within our physical body to
talk about extended active inference
beyond skulls
yes so um
[Music]
we can think about like
that great point which is that nested
systems of which we often talk about can
actually be thought of as extended
active inference systems
so
we've talked about like ant nest mates
in the ant colony
and so there's the sense in which the
lateral interactions from one nest
mate's point of view
because those lateral interactions are
with other nest mates there's cognition
on both sides of the interaction so it
is like an extended active inference
process
and then also there's the
extended active inference with the
physical substrate and the stigma g and
the building of the nest architecture
and the pheromone deposition
and that kind of physical substrate is
more on the mere active inference rather
than adaptive active inference end of
the spectrum and the physical substrate
reminds us more of figure one
where you have an active cognitive
entity
that's doing some sort of free energy
minimizing process that's helping it
select policy that's the arg min
and then it's feeding into
the dynamics of the external niche which
can be complex and they have their own
endogenous change dynamics which is seen
by the fact that like the rate of change
on the external states
is a function of
something involving the current state of
those
world states plus a noise term
so this can be a complex recursive
non-linear function but that could still
be a mere active entity because it's not
actually engaged in a policy selection
rather just a complex dynamical
unfolding
and then in contrast in figure 2
we see that the external states
are still taking similar arguments
eta and a
so the current states at that time
and actions feeding into it that's
what's influencing external states and
we see those arguments are still here
actions feeding in from the entity and
the current state of the external states
except what it's doing is no longer just
the rate of change is a function of plus
noise
but an active policy selection
more like the kind that the entity is
involved in so maybe figure two is
reminding us more of like two nest mates
interacting with each other in figure
one is more like a nest may interacting
with the physical stigmergic niche
and so in that way it opens up all of
the discussions we've had about
multi-scale active
and nested systems
and thinking about them
as extended active inference dean
yeah in the paper
i'll just read one sentence from the
paper it says here the concept of the
cognitive niche that we refer to
here
is a sort of hybrid
between the concepts of
the selective
developmental
and cognitive niches
it's right near the beginning yeah yep
right there
yeah you got it
so
in the context of what we're in those
two figures there
when we're talking hybrid what are we
really talking about we're talking about
the comparison of say the electric
component of the engine and the internal
combustion
engine that are both in one car
would that be a good analogy in terms of
being able to figure out
what part of this is the um
is the vessel one part of this is the
electric motor and what part of this
is the internal combustion motor would
that be a good um
metaphor for what we're talking about
what's the car
right
well that's
that's the is that the culture piece i'm
not sure
yeah i don't know what a cognitive niche
is here like i don't know if i want to
entail culture with a cognitive niche
because this is what this paper is about
or whether i want to entail cognitive
niche with culture which is something
that we've talked about in a whole bunch
of papers right so that's a good
question i don't know
it reminds me of your earlier um
statements about how like if a pizza is
uh something with toppings on top and
then if you put it upside down is it
still a pizza so
is car
the total functional phenomena involving
vehicular transport
or
at what point does that also require
like gravity and a road and all these
other pieces that are part of the
extended process by which cars come to
be like is the factory that made the car
part of the car
i mean it would
be interesting if they just blinked into
existence but because things are part of
process ontologies
how can we
connect this question of extended
function
to
the
process and object ontology um angle
okay cool blue i see some stigma g
happening
um
okay so
to kind of close this little
thread on
applying extended active inference
though of course we
welcome a thousand more specific
contributions and we hope to continue
building these actual models and
examples and
interactive dashboards and everything
out
there are multiple ways
to think about what is extended
and probably even for consensus on the
same
perspective on the world as it really is
or even on the same choice of models
there would still be a lot of degrees of
freedom in how we actually apply
extended active inference but one
tantalizing cue there from blue was like
connecting it to the scale-free scale
friendly components and potentially
connecting what we've been talking about
with active inference in nested
multi-scale systems to this perspective
on thinking about their niche as
consisting of other mere figure 1 or
adaptive figure 2 active entities
what do we see with the termites
so
i just was thinking about like the
literal um
pushing off
into the niche in in kind of like this
scale-free
slash skill-friendly way
i
saw
the last author of
these papers give
a talk at the mathematics of collective
intelligence workshop and it was so cool
like really literally like the termite
mound
and i'm sure that the ants nests do the
same thing daniel but i think that the
they're not very studyable because as
soon as you go in to start to try to
figure them out like they fall apart is
that that's true so we kind of get a
better
um well many termites build
underground and in logs so it can be
hard to assess above ground termite
architecture is of course amazing and
more ant architecture is happening
underground which makes it really hard
to study unless you have like a high
resolution land landmine sweeping device
land mine sweeping devices so like are
there like images i mean yeah i don't
see how to do it really without
destroying it because they're like made
of sand right so how do you like i mean
i remember like when we were kids there
was like the frame the two glass panes
and you would get some ants and like
throw them in there and watch them like
dig tunnels but like other than this
like very artificial environment
like the deer on the trampoline right
other than this very artificial
environment you know in what way do we
know about the ant architecture but but
my point was actually just that that the
termites um really like you can predict
the behavior of the termites based on
like the velocity of the wind and how
hot or cool or like they build all these
different structures and you can predict
like and they not only build these
different structures but they will
actually like deconstruct their mound
and then reconstruct it like based on
whatever whatever's shifting in the
environment and so this latest paper is
called like really shows the um
it gets into like the math behind
how termites termite mounds are
constructed like under what you know
wind velocity and so forth but um i just
thought that that was a really neat
uh example of
literally putting
the offloading into i mean we literally
do that as humans and so we're pretty
familiar with like you know the
smartphone and the different ways in
which we do
cognitive uploading but this idea of
cognitive uploading which i've always
used cognitive offloading
cognitive uploading into the niche
can kind of tell others even future
others uh what was happening to you in
your life it's like you're writing your
own little you know history book as we
are cognitively uploading these videos
onto youtube you know this will be here
after we're gone uh but the termites do
this too in a very cool like physical
way
i just have a scene
tucker has corrected me in chat it's not
a landmine sweeping device it's an ant
mind sweeping device so thank you tucker
cool
yes i think um extended active inference
systems to study could include
starting with uh
colony
like systems or various other systems
what would be another good place to now
jump in as we sort of walk back to the
midden pile walk back to the trash sheep
of ideas and then figure out where to
repurpose and
go back in um maybe
you meant yes dean well i just have a
question for both of you because so
when i think of offloading and they give
the example and i think i put the image
up there of the brain on top of the of
the phone
um
if we if we upload and we're talking
about intergenerational stuff
are we uploading into culture and is
that the diff is that the primary
difference between offloading something
so i don't have to remember it
and uploading something so that
rules are introduced that you
will sort of be
swept up by if you join this culture i'm
asking because i'm not really sure i i
was trying to figure that out myself
what's the is there an arbitrariness to
this or is it really kind of clear what
the line is in terms of they tried to
explain it
is it yeah they said it's akin to
cognitive uploading
but it's different so where did you guys
come away on that on that question of
what what's different about it
yes
great question thank you dean let's look
at what they
wrote and then let's see where we can
take it so they wrote cognitive
uploading is akin to cognitive
offloading in the original theory of the
extended mind
however in contrast to the traditional
notion of offloading
the notion of uploading refers to the
creation of novel cognitive functions
that are taken on board by the cognitive
niche per se
instead of being merely managed by the
cognitive niche a function's offloaded
when individual agents restructure their
world
so as to minimize internal processing
costs and or increase reliability
so offloading like you could offload
your heavy heavy backpack and just drop
it on the floor so offloading has more
of a sense um at least
hopefully this is the line with as
they're describing it of like
it is allowing the shelves in the world
to you're offloading what you're
carrying into places in the world
and so the cognitive onus
and the imperative for epistemic action
is still resting in the entity of
interest so cognitive offloading could
be consistent with a world view that's
like solipsistic like there's just this
one cognitive entity and they're like
offloading they're off-gassing it's
their exhaust thermal waste they're
offloading cognition to the niche
cognitive uploading
takes on more of a sense
that there's actually something active
on the other side because like if you're
gonna upload a file to a cloud folder
there has to be another server that's
actually recognizing your packets
as you're uploading that file
so
uploading is more consistent with the
framing that they have for example in
figure 2 surprise surprise whereas the
cognitive offloading
could be consistent with figure one like
i'm
trying to have this cognitive function
of this symphony of bells being played
and so i'm gonna set up these dominoes
and these delays in the niche and where
to put the sheet music and where to put
the post-it notes
offloading the cognitive requirements
making it extended making it distributed
in figure 2 it goes even a step further
and that's what they're trying to
highlight the distinction with with
their usage of the word uploading
because there's actually something
that's cognitive that's
accepting
the download
or the upload from the entity is the
download from the server so to speak so
sorry if that's repetitive but i think
it's a subtle and important point dean
yeah i think it's a super important
point too so then
then for me the question is so
let's say that i have an academic
culture that i could upload to and i
also have a professional culture that i
could upload to let's say they're two
different things
right
so i i've got
i'm i'm a part-time student and i'm also
working
full-time at my job every day is there
some way of being able to
find myself or find examples of myself
not being downloaded on per se by each
one of those different cultures
but me uploading into both of those and
retaining my sort of hybridized sense of
the world so from a psychological and a
functional niche perspective
what does that entail for me as the
person who's now kind of
doing this oscillation back and forth
between these two niche constructions
right now they again they don't go to
that length here but i think i think
it's important based on what you just
said daniel for us to remember it isn't
just a single culture
examination here at the whole point is
is that there are multiple niche
constructions happening
all the time and it's just a matter of
whether or not we recognize
the differences
right so
i don't again i'm not sure that they
answer that here but um
i think we're getting closer to being
able to find that answer because of what
they're
what they're bringing to our attention
so just on that on that point um
when i really was thinking about
cognitive uploading it's like um
it's like putting something into
the niche
for others to use and reuse and maybe
interact with or like remix and what
you're saying about like this
hybridization between academic and
professional really makes me think about
complex systems and like the santa fe
institute where daniel and i met and
um the
kind of
siloed
academic experience that uh maybe people
are still having unfortunately but that
that people have had so if you are in
you know mechanical engineering versus
biology versus economics like you have
very different
knowledge
acquisition and like a very different
culture and a very different way of
interacting with your peers
and there's this kind of like siloed
culture even within an academic culture
so like even subsections of academia
tend to be siloed and when you bring
people into a complex systems kind of
environment there's this amazing like
ability for new ideas to generate right
it's like this cross-fertilization or
cross-pollination people call it
different things but but when people
come together with academic expertise
some you know shared ability to read
write and do some mathematics so when
people come together with and intermixed
their own siloed
knowledge which is deep like it tends to
be very very deep like if you've got you
know phd or bachelor's degree or
master's degree in in your field like
you know a whole lot about that field
and probably not a lot like about the
other field so when you come together in
a complex system kind of way it it
enables people with this deep deep
knowledge and understanding of their own
thing to then interact and it's exciting
and it builds new things like i think
exponentially like like you know if i
get together with a bunch of other data
scientists or a bunch of other
bio people or narrow people i don't have
that same kind of
excited brainstormy
jittery idea
gush
like that was so professional um
but but
generally i think that that happens in
this cross fertilization or
cross-pollination
way and when i think about cognitive
uploading i think about like you push it
in
so that other people can interact with
it so that other people so that it can
do the cross-fertilization thing and
maybe that's just kind of my naive
interpretation of what they were saying
in the paper but that's kind of what i
got um and then daniel made us slides so
perfect i talked enough i i totally um
one slidesworth in kairos time totally
agreed though like
uploading as opposed to or as
distinguished from offloading offloading
you just need to trust that the shelf
isn't going to break and someone's not
going to steal your backpack while
you're gone but cognitive uploading like
you got to trust that file is being
stored and that that is going to be able
to be executed potentially even outside
of your
awareness or control so when we're in
like a interdisciplinary context or just
sharing like cognition in a team or
getting it done as a team
the uploading brings in this whole
element of like trust and culture and
glue that others are going to be able to
do things that you don't want to do that
you can't do that you wouldn't see of
doing
all these different ways in which their
active cognitive model
is different
and importantly aligned and importantly
contrasting and complementary it's all
of those things
so here's a few visualizations of
borders between
um or interfaces between entities and
each other or entities in the niche
so on the left side it's like the
overlap between two systems whether we
think about them as like oh that block
in the city it's part of um little italy
and downtown
so there could be like a block there's a
border region but it is both included in
the two sets or it can be a little bit
more
blurry or fuzzy around what those orange
and blue sets are but still there's like
a region that is overlapping and claimed
by both
there's another case where
the border or the interface is something
that is like overlapping to both but
also a distinct region
perhaps like a cell membrane or
in the full separation case
it becomes its own
separate region
and that entails now this recursive
boundary setting because now there's
wall street there's the street in front
of the wall and
so this just
made me wonder um when we were talking
about
academic and professional
what kind of synthesis
or what kind of integration are we
looking for
which one of these setups
is predisposed towards effective
extended active inference
or
is this something that we determine
about how it really is in the world
hashtag realism
is this a model selection choice
from an instrumentalist point of view
can i just speak to that for a second i
think this is interesting because
in in this example and also in the paper
where they talk about desire lines we do
have a tendency to sort of see these
things be at the border or the the the
artifact of the number of
humans or or animals that walked to the
watering hole and the result on that and
they speak to that clearly in the paper
that
so sometimes that is is not acting in
the surprise the environment's not
acting in a surprising way
it that's the result of what ends up
happening with a whole bunch of people
follow the same path or use the same
stones to break the nuts that's the
capuchin monkey example
or use the same spices right and in a
particular
thing one one of the things that we kind
of just touched on briefly in this dot
zero was so what if you took all of
those examples that you had a boundary
and you used green as a as one of the
things to sort of show it in the
rectangular shape but what if you were
able to twist that
and and do with it what we have when we
for example use the um
the mobius strip in the keywords
do you have a representation of that
here and why would that matter because i
think that actually really does matter
and i think it's something that we tend
to overlook
so if we're talking about i mean if
we're talking about transdisciplinary
and blues point i think this fits
really really well but if you wanted to
talk about people walking into a
situation
who are creating a new cognitive niche
um
they don't come from a place of knowing
they basically come from a place of not
knowing
and they're going
to build that new boundary or that new
border and they're not going to be
restricted to the oval shape
they might be able to put a single twist
on it and come up with
like like i said the example that we
have that we put up as a representation
behind our keywords or maybe they'll do
a mandelbrotty in
two cranks of the system and
they'll come up with the um
two loops that are
orthogonal to one another right and and
what does that mean in terms of a
representation around uploading as
opposed to
offloading and i think that that's yeah
exactly as you're building it out here
this is where it actually gets
interesting because i think that's where
if again if we always see ourselves as
where did where does my cognition end
and begin
we will get one
out we'll kick a certain number of
representations all conforming to that
pre-desire to keep it the cognition
contained and framed and stabilized now
if we look at this from the environment
position and the argument flipper
inversion of that
can we just limit the inversions to
the
the two sides on either side of the
markov blanket or could we actually look
at the markup blanket twisting and
reforming itself
because i mean it opens up the space for
that possibility now whether we choose
to give any attention over to that or
make ourselves available to that
it gets really really interesting in a
hurry
look
so
i think it is really interesting and
where we put the boundary
um maybe depends on what we feel that we
are
uploading or offloading like by us
uploading
these video series into
the niche environment of the internet
um
we other people are able to cognitively
offload like they're offloading
their need to
delve into deep read and unpack this
paper like they could just you know
they've offloaded it to us and they're
just watching the youtube video not
everybody sorry if you if you're really
actually reading the paper and really
into it and just
want to hear someone else reflect but in
many ways you know we provide a summary
that that
in today's information latent age it's
really impossible to just read all the
papers even in your own field when
there's five papers released a day so i
don't blame you for doing some cognitive
offloading there but by us uploading
that enables someone else to offload is
that always the case is there like this
interplay with upload and offload like i
think about google maps like that is
the biggest cognitive offload that i've
seen in technologically in technological
advancements in my lifetime like i no
longer remember how to get anywhere like
maybe if i drive there 15 times
maybe then but or maybe if i know
someplace next to it like like but if as
far as driving to a new place a place
i've never been a new housing
development for example like i have a
friend that moves in and i've never been
there before i'm at their house 15 times
before i remember how to get back and
forth and i google that myself the whole
way every time
it's massive cognitive offloading but
only because google was so kind to
upload
the information only due to uploading
can i then offload and then does that
also work culturally like in terms of i
think about
institutional or hierarchical
organizations or even thinking like a
state i have someone who will make shoes
for me i don't need to know how to make
shoes i just need to know how to access
shoes i don't know how to make shoes so
but because someone else is uploading
that information technology their
product to our culture
cognitively but it's like the output of
their cognition
actually i get it maybe they could
actually teach someone else how to make
shoes if they had to but but my point is
is that there's like this interchange
does upload somewhat because you upload
it to someone else download it and then
they can offload because of their
ability to download
sorry if that was rambly no i think that
that's i think that's perfect and my
question then is from a learning
standpoint are we more adept at
accepting other people's
information because that expedites we
can follow and and
use that
your first example
right
here's somebody
google i mean for google it's great for
them they cannot they they went and
figured out how to become the go-to
source for uploading
but what are we doing in terms of giving
people
a sense of their agency over uploading
as opposed to simply just following and
being consumed by the googles if we're
going to invert this we need to ask that
question around what learning what we're
giving people in terms of agency and and
knowing the difference between
the trade-offs
that happen with offloading as you
described um you're not building any
desire lines
your your gps is doing it for you
now now you feel completely dependent
upon that thing and you don't have to be
able to make shoes to be able to
understand the difference between what
you might need in one set of
circumstances on your feet and what you
might need on a in another circumstance
set of circumstances on your feet but
are we drifting to that place that says
i don't even know what shoes to put on
today i better go and find out from
google
yes very interesting um
keeping with the uh uploading offloading
desire paths and google thanks youtube
by the way for the affordance
what if each person were only seeing
locally which paths were attractive to
them which search results were appealing
to them
but then there was uh an eye in the sky
that could see the statistical
distributions of everyone else in their
uploading and offloading
that would actually make that
a tremendous resource for
the eye in the sky and so that's a
little bit of the asymmetry but the
challenge and opportunity
um also the caption of figure one
does explicitly mention like action
perception and learning
so that's very
interesting and it does raise the
question of
what
is the difference between perception and
learning which is discussed a ton in
active and in the textbook what the
similarities and difference are like
with perception being over faster time
scales but being fundamentally similar
to learning but learning being about
cognitive parameters and usually
updating over slower time skills
and then what does learning look like
in a cognitive offload
world
in the no offload world
then in the cognitive offload world and
then in the cognitive upload world so
just to kind of maybe just give one
example um the no offload world is the
test where you can't bring any notes in
yeah in that case it's like what you
know about organic chemistry is in your
school
it one could
go a little bit broader than that but
you can't take in your notes the
cognitive offloading
which is going to beg the question of
like epistemic action is you're allowed
to bring in your own notes or even the
textbook so it's a dead artifact in the
niche it's a mere active entity it's an
epistemic resource in eos we would call
an informational entity in the niche and
it can be referenced and you might only
have to learn where to look
learn where you put your backpack learn
which chapter to look to when you want
to resolve a certain kind of uncertainty
so it's an affordance you didn't have in
the no offload case to have the textbook
or the notes
what's the cognitive upload is it phone
a friend
is it
go in with
the chemicals and have a lab kit like
what does it look like to go one step
beyond yes you can take your notes into
that organic chemistry test
what is the upload what do you think
dean
i think the upload is when you are are
taking the information that you've
received here and finding yourself
migrating in
a completely different culture and
somebody in that completely different
culture says
um i want you to solve this problem for
me before i can hire you
can you do this this thing first show me
that you can do this thing or resolve
this
this issue for me
so it's it's taking information from one
context
and finding yourself in a completely
different context not from the person
who's decided this is the amount of
material that we've covered in these
past 13 weeks and now i'm going to
select out the points that i want you to
as you said load into your into your
bucket and carry into the testing
situation i want you actually now to
take what you've learned and i want you
to be able to go out back into the wild
now
where
you're gonna have to be able to solve
something as a result of you
loading loading up your your
quiver or your
your 13 weeks worth of information right
that's the that's literally finding
yourself
now working with a new culture and that
new culture
taking on all the properties that
they're talking about in this paper
another um angle on that oh yes blue
please
so my take on that would be to
like say you have all of the material
that you learned you have all the books
you have all the notes
you then go teach it to someone else and
they go in and take the test for you so
that would be
uploading
awesome awesome is that what you were
gonna say
yeah so we have too much we do too much
i was thinking of a driver's exam it's
the difference between the no notes
driver's exam taking the test at the dmv
can people tell that i just renewed my
license
and then there's the having the notes
and then there's the actual driving and
so that is where the functions are no
longer hypothetical and in a testing
scenario but they're enacted
and that means that it's different to
say you should do this when you're
parallel parking and it is going to be
15 feet versus the actual enacting of it
and that cognitive function
really or instrumentally
is happening in this extended way with
the
visual components of the car and the
proprioception of the car so that is one
angle is towards the practice bench and
then blue awesome point with taking it
towards the teaching which is like if if
you had to send a proxy and what if we
all had to train a proxy tax test taker
um it would take like well you know it
when you can teach it to another level
because that would entail
many many
aspects of making sure that you could
upload it in a way where then they could
offload or um
not and then of course the infinite
regress is what if they had to go train
somebody else and then um you would have
reinvented academia from scratch dean
yeah i i find that what you got what you
guys are describing i find that kind of
is an intermediary step where if you can
teach it to somebody else
you know it and i and i think it does a
good job of blending sort of the
procedural knowledge and the declarative
part if you can teach it to somebody
else but i think if you're talking about
uploading i think you actually need to
find yourself in a completely different
cultural setting
if as opposed to the offloading aspect
of it so i think you actually have to
move
outside of the
the teaching realm i find i find that if
you can teach it to somebody else
as a nice
as a nice sort of middle ground between
where you would eventually have to go if
you're going to
niche construct
in the wild
as opposed to the setting which is
somewhat contained and framed which is
teaching right learn learning in that
setting
so i'm not i'm not saying you're you
guys aren't
moving in that direction i just think
that the ultimate end game of uploading
is different than the one that's
offloading which there's way more
offloading in the teaching realm then we
probably care to acknowledge
or
for the um plot embedding
offloading is more like instructionalism
you're offloading the recipe
and then interactionism requires the
other interact ant to be a cognitive
entity and so that's more like a figure
two it's more like cognitive uploading
and the more
interactionism is at play the more
figure two like we're in a space of
the more it is like a question that dave
has just asked in the chat which is
isn't the result of offloading
a new goal seeking self-maintaining
autopoetic thing
all caps and and telki that's kind of
aristotelian a little bit i believe
um yes and that's a little bit like um
our
progression here here was two things and
their interface
and then it got more and more shared or
delineated or less
until at some level of interfacing and
interactionism and extended cognition
from a functional or psychological
perspective which is what they explore
in this paper or from an ecological and
an evolutionary perspective like
constant at all explore elsewhere it
does become a new kind of thing the
eukaryotic cell
is a thing and it's a thing that
involves these nested and interfacing
systems and then i took the colors that
we had here
and overlaid them
from
this
abstract space
into
this kind of space that we've seen with
the figure one and two representations
and isn't that interesting
that the blanket states
are the interface the border states
and so
as we discussed
the dynamics even in the mere active
case
could be very chaotic or very difficult
for the entity to predict so mere active
shouldn't be seen as meaning that it's
like simple or it doesn't have rich
dynamics
how do we know which of these settings
we're in or how do we make the best of
these settings
wasn't there daniel can you find the
slide in the 41 deck where we talked
about the joint
yes there we go the joint
self-evidencing i think i i guess i'm i
i guess what i'm saying is is that joint
self-evidencing on one level of
instructionalism or the joint
self-evidencing in terms of the
interaction piece
um
i think that that's
you you can decide how big how how how
sophistic how complicated you want that
joint to be and i think that that's what
this is essentially saying is can we get
ourselves to a place of
this closest like
the closing of the circle of causality
part right that sort of circularity
piece of this
when do we when do we realize that it's
circular is it when we're at the
instructionalist level or when we're at
the
level
blue do you have a thought or there's a
little bit more slide play that could
happen i think to resolve dean's
question
uh go ahead and give it over to dean i'm
just i'm thinking
let's say that we were in a forest of
f2s
so we're no longer thinking about just
nest mates
interacting but now we're thinking about
like
each one of these
orange
so we're gonna our system of interest is
gonna be the orange um guys we got f2a
f2b and f2c
and they're like different evolutionary
replicators of a similar kind there are
different organisms
the blue could be the same physical
niche it could be each other in an
adaptive niche they could each be in
their own
battles
but their fitness is being relatively
compared in terms of their success
now
what does it mean when on that side that
we were just on
on figure two
when uh they mentioned
this closes the circle of causality in
which the niche and phenotypes are
trying to learn about each other to
minimize their joint free energy or
surprise okay yeah so what does that
mean that the causality has been closed
so one worldview would be well let's
just look at how the three orange
entities are connected and think about
how they're in competition
and so that might be a totally valid and
important way to look at it but
um
this is kind of like there's various
statements i'm sure various phrasings
but i won't even try but what is the
good
in
doing so well in the orange
f2a free energy minimization
such that this whole system
is actually maladaptive
so that would be like this entity
being greedy
in this new kind of interaction or thing
and so
the one
uh the orange
a b or c
that's going to persist the best or have
the highest fitness
is going to be involved in the best free
energy minimization of this whole system
where there's sense and action coming
both ways
because just to short term do a free
energy minimization here
at the cost of maladaptive actions
coming in the future back from the niche
is not a sustainable strategy and so
that's like where they tuck the little
bit the last thread
gets tucked back into the ecology and
evolution and the selective niche which
is the one that actually provides
at least an adaptive starting point for
the cognitive functional and
psychological habitats that they're
discussing
what do you think dean
well
so
so again here's the thing if we're
talking about just the perception piece
and we've got three
three versions of perception is that
what you're
you're trying to bring out here
three similar kinds of entities that are
involved in
[Music]
fitness
okay but we're focusing on that but
we're focusing in on the on the
perception aspect of that are are you
not
or are we looking at the cultural piece
of this when three perceivers are
proximal to one another in in
in in an environmental cluster or in a
cognitive niche how do those perceptions
align with one another and what's the
time frame right what's the diacronic of
this
i just want to make sure i'm clear about
what you're
what you're trying to show here
there's probably
multiple ways to think about it or show
it let's let's try to make it one one
little bit clearer
okay here's going to be the blue niche
and now we're going to have
those cognitive entities sharing a niche
so
so here's going to be a bunch of brains
that are going to be sharing the same
blue niche
okay so
how does this affect what you're
discussing
they're all being interfaced with a
common niche
and so in what way can we say that
they're involved in joint action
perception
loops
well that's that's what i'm that's where
i'm where i'm curious because i think it
does what this does is it shows that
there is something called an extended
and extended
aspect of this of this
active inference frame but i wouldn't i
don't know how each one of those
perceivers
realizes
what the others
are perceiving as well i think
the environment or the niche itself
knows
collectively what that is but i don't
know that each one of those
individual representations of the brain
necessarily does know and i think this
is where this it trips up a lot of
people because oh i don't believe in
extended uh
extended cognition
because you can't pause daniel you can't
possibly know what dean's thinking and
dean can't possibly know what blue's
thinking but eventually as we work out
together through communication through
some sort of signaling processes
eventually we we kind of land on it on
some sort of generally agreed to
sense there's a collective sense around
this as well and so do we stay well that
collective sense isn't cognition
and we don't know what it is but it's
not cognition
but of course it's all based on
cognition
but we're not going to call it cognition
because
we can't possibly know everything that's
going on in that other perceiver
cognizer's
way of looking at blue at this blue
rectangle right
so sorry sorry blue knight blue
rectangle
right so i again i this is that's yeah
thinking through other minds i don't
know how i don't know how
we
i don't know how we quantify it
but neces but also recognize that it is
it does exist
and if we get if we get
to to
um concerned that if we can't
measure it it's not a thing
then we'll just pretend like it's not
there
but it it's there and not all things are
necessarily measurable
the way that we can hook up the the
cap and make sure that it's
picking up everything in
in the whatever it is rather whatever
the heck of the one is that is the cap
as opposed to the fmri i don't know
eeg
thank you sir yes um i i just looked up
like
opposite of extended
and so there's like retracted reduced
shrunk
narrowed shortened
it's interesting how extended cognition
feels like a reach
yet
defending
the other position
is almost too narrow
yeah
blue
so i just was
going back and reading the author's
definition of
uploading versus offloading
um
and they said in contrast to the
traditional notion of offloading the
notion of uploading refers to the
creation of
novel cognitive functions that are taken
on board by the cognitive niche per se
instead of being merely managed by the
cognitive niche a function is offloaded
when individual agents restructure the
world so as to minimize internal
processing costs and or increase
reliability
for example by posting a yellow sticky
note
as a reminder a function
for example that a function is uploaded
when social and technological change
means that it's now taken of care of by
the niche rather than the individual for
example most agents store phone numbers
in smartphones instead of by memory so
the whole number storage function has
been assimilated into the niche
uh the niche into which the function has
been uploaded can then be passed on to
future generations for them to leverage
share and finesse that function and so i
wonder if the difference between
offloading and uploading
is a transgenerational difference
so like i do offloading
um like you know with my yellow sticky
note or or like my notes and my little
pad but i do offloading when i you know
create a publication from those notes
and publish it into something that's
then archived that the future
generations can access
that's that's awesome
um here's a thought on that
uh connecting it to the epistemic
actions so offloading
just like they describe it says um a
yellow stick note on the front door to
remind them to pick up milk next time
they are out
it doesn't say
this means pick up milk they've
offloaded their cognitive backpack but
only they know their recovery seed only
they know the password
to
speak friend and enter into
that extended cognitive function
whereas if it were cognitively uploaded
i made an app that reminds people
to get their milk when they're low
that is actually something that because
of its intrinsic and more integrated
actual cognitive function like the
ability to assess information like the
level of milk in the fridge and then
take an action like remind the person or
not
it's a bonafide
cognitive entity
it's more like figure two more like
uploading than it is like figure one
offloading and then that app
can be leveraged and shared and
intergenerational
in a way where it would be extremely
difficult and only through like implicit
learning and seeing it many times would
somebody be like ah yes we put the
yellow post-it note when we want to
remind ourselves later so
interesting example and it's very true
what they say about future generations
dean
yeah and i think when we get into that
that diacronic piece
we're not just we're not just
offloading remo remember to get milk
what we're doing is we're
when we're uploading we're talking about
rules especially if we're talking about
culture it's the old
that's not the way we do things around
here kind of thing
so
i think
there's there's a there are differences
between offloading and uploading
and i do believe that
rules because rules are always kind of
flexible they're always a limit around
where when we talk about scale
friendliness there's an effective
limit around how a rule will be able to
function
at scale
so there's there is going to be a
certain amount of arbitrariness when we
get up to that rules place and as we
pass rules down from one generation to
the next i'm sure both of you can think
of the times when your parents told you
this is the rule and you both looked at
them and went
what the
why is that the rule
oh okay i'm so now when we're talking
about rules and we're talking about
uploaded things
i think there has to be a certain amount
of participation in that rule setting
it's not always the case
but i think in order for it to be
adopted and actually to be a part of the
cognitive niche we're not just talking
about content here we're talking about
consequences here as well and so i think
that's where this gets really really
interesting in terms of building or
constructing that psychological and
functional niche but how also
appreciating that it's kind of
rules-based and it's joint
self-evidencing as opposed to well
daniel just believes in
in
jitsi right so everybody's got to follow
daniel's rule
but that's not kind of how it works when
you bring a bunch of people together and
you're trying to come up with some sense
of where it is where is where are the
cognitive
where are the cognitive limits here that
arbitrariness aspect of it is actually a
part of the game
so that
is awesome it connects the
intergenerational niche inheritance
to the interactionism
and to that idea of having to teach
somebody else to take your organic
chemistry test is the point of rule
following in the short term from the age
of you know zero to six years old to
minimize the perceived number of times
that a rule is violated
or is it to minimize the amount of times
that your grandchildren
violate that rule or for example and so
the further one looks into the future
the more interactionist it looks and the
more
autonomy potentially provided to the
recipient and that might also connect
back to mike levin the discussion on
training and learning
because the the trainer
and the trained
that may be a functional dyad but it may
not be able to result in the trainee
being able to be
training somebody else whereas somebody
who has learned has a generative model
update and so they might be able to
teach
and then also to connect to um
dean's uh let's uh it was academic and
professional
settings right and we talked about like
the hybrid models
and about um okay so we had the
we had walking into new niches then we
had the professional okay
here
is us and now we're engaging
we can think of this in of course
multiple ways
so one of this would be diachronic
so the diachronic interpretation
would be grandparent
parent
child
this the synchronic but extended spatial
interpretation
would be this could all be happening at
the same time here's the academic
context academic niche
me in the academic niche
professional niche
other professionals in the niche
so we have through space and through
time
just like they explored some of those
dimensions in the paper what do either
of you think about that
the representation i think it's
like like this extended act of
difference it it grows right it
it blossoms
so i'm liking where it's going
so it just made me um think about like
so i had brought up the temporal um you
know maybe to be uploading versus
offloading there's some kind of temporal
persistence but
also like what if
to be uploading it has to be accessible
even in the same time because we don't
really know if our youtube video is
going to be around in 10 years or
watched by anyone else except us or we
don't really know um but but we do uh
know that it's watched by like tucker
was watching it i guess and dave and and
so there are some people watching it so
so if uploading just means
beyond personal use would that be fair
like is that is that uploading um versus
offloading
i don't know um but then if i
if i remind my daughter like so so it
just makes me think of like but what
about this but what about this so if i
remind my daughter like hey don't forget
your lunch or hey you know you need to
study for your spelling test if i remind
her
or if i create a reminder for her is
that
uploading or offloading
here's your lunch
here's a post-it
to remind
of lunch
how will you
remind yourself of your lunch
and it probably there's probably ones
that we could add above here is your
lunch
um here's the food in your mouth
here's the airplane flying in in the
food in your mouth
or even before
yeah
well before here's your lunch i need to
remember to remind my daughter to
get her lunch
so there's like how am i gonna remember
to remind my daughter to get her lunch
like there's that whole like second tier
of that
yeah
yes
yes um and this is kind of like a
continuum on the um well this is a
preparatory
uh preamble but then it's like a
continuum again from the more
instructionalist
to the more interactionist
um
and it probably gets more
allegorical and it gets more flexible
it gets more empowering but if you say
and you mean it how um
i'm gonna let you decide how to remind
yourself of how to get your lunch
but also if you forget your lunch
you know it's gonna be really bad
then that creates a cognitive tension
and so that's kind of like where it's
okay to experiment and fail and
interaction
you know to improvise one must
like make some notes they didn't intend
and then continue to roll with it as
their new
state and just continue on
like in improv versus if it was just
about playing the sheet music as written
then every time a mistake is made
one could just
push the rails back in
so i think what you're saying is i need
to let my daughter go hungry when she
forgets her lunch because right now if
she forgets her lunch it's really bad
for me because i have to drive like an
extra hour to go home and get the lunch
or it's either way it's an hour out of
my day i've got to stop at the grocery
store and assemble lunch it's not just
lunch it's like lunch plus like six
different snacks that she eats
throughout the day so she has to bring
all the food with her every day so it's
really bad for me if she forgets so um
because i end up taking care of it for
her i should just let her starve and
then i will have uploaded that task
without getting between mother and
daughter can i just say one quick thing
here
um i think again if we're if we're just
trying to figure out what the extended
cognition if
if there's evidence for extended
cognition
it's probably in
the rule
and the consequence so it's to your
point blue if there's a consequence here
who has to take that consequence on
the older person who
who who maybe whose prospective memory
didn't
work out that day and didn't provide all
the reminders or the younger person
who now is
has the effect of not having something
to eat but i think the point here in
terms of can we
the argument because they call it an
argument this paper is an argument the
argument for
extended cognition
would be one where
if we upload we're probably going to be
uploading rules
and the consequences of those rules are
implied
versus the uploading of content and
material that tends to overwhelm us
and that we use devices then to act as a
way of being able to store because our
own memorial capacities are
are somewhat limited like i mean when i
compare my memorial capacity to you and
daniel i i can't hold a candle to that
right so i should be the one using all
of the instruments for that
but what i do is i have my own way of
sort of compensating for that by
developing my own rules sooner
and with with a more um
consequential nature to that right so
that's what one of the things we could
possibly be teaching six to
eight-year-olds
not just here are the rules
but what can you do in terms of helping
me who's probably got less capacity as i
get older for remembering all the
content
so there's consequences for me now and
there's consequences for you we both
suffer a certain consequence in this new
environmental niche that we're
constructing
now maybe the eight-year-old doesn't
give a rat's backside about that she's
just hangry now but
oh well right i mean so there's going to
be some learning one way or another and
it could be through guilt or it can be
through some kind of a conversation
where you actually do introduce the
rules and the consequences i don't know
in comparison to memorizing the rgb
values of an image like the pixel colors
none of us have memories that hold the
candle to even the smallest jpeg
so
render onto the jpeg that which is
jpegable
and then what will that leave humans to
do
and
we hear about cognitive overload
cognitive security of course
what does that actually mean
for designing informational niches
cognitive niches from the psychological
functional ecological selective
perspectives that are not overwhelming
or that are accessible or that are
resilient or that do stabilize function
there's so many awesome
questions that this like brings us
totally
towards
daniel i'm sorry but i'm gonna have to
bounce out now because uh
i've just kind of used up all my energy
anyway close this swing i hope you guys
can close this thing off for me and i
look forward to the point too so thanks
thank you dean peace all right all right
cool
blue
let's uh think for a few more minutes
what could be fun
4.2
and just how we can
go from
some of the rhetoric and perspectives
they share towards
all of these extremely relevant
scenarios that we've been
discussing
like
yeah
so for me i think i'd like to touch back
on to um
what other situations are like the
elizabethan
play
people like the elizabethan cast
the theater company that's what it is
sorry uh
so what other situations are like this
elizabethan theater company in that
the culture is so
strong and so
vital to participation
that um
you can just wing it like you can know a
lot of things just by cueing off of
others
so i had mentioned jazz i don't know
what else um what other i'd like to look
at that a little bit more because is
that that was the example that they gave
right this this diaconic cognition so it
would be cool to look at that
uh a little more deeply
yes
especially in like the kind of online
context um
[Music]
yes
um
agreed about that yeah you brought up
music and jazz and about culture where
does what is culture of different kinds
and where does that fit into
this ability
of people to have a joint action
in what ways or in what senses is
culture about shared ways of thinking
orthodoxy heterodoxy
in what ways is culture about joint
action
orthopraxis and heteropraxis
so i was thinking also about action um
and like action off-loading
uh uh because just like in terms of a
scaled system like sure cells do their
own actions like they eat food and they
you know secrete nutrients and you know
they like communicate with each other
and whatever but but in terms of like a
nested system
um
like the cells don't have to go find
water the water just comes to them
right like like whereas a human it's
like one of the most vital things that
we could ever do is find water like
clean drinking water super necessary for
life
so
we have to do that i mean we've
offloaded that into our culture with
running water but not every human
but i just think about we're acting on
behalf of organ systems cell systems
organelles et cetera
so i think about action off-loading so
what does that look like um
yes and how how akin to cognitive
offloading or uploading is that
yes in what ways is the cognitive
offloading and uploading
[Music]
that of perception
in what ways is it offloading action
like if you write a script
that then
does some daily task
that could be seen as like offloading a
repetitive action
and that's something that
we're only unlocking with computers
but it's kind of like a and it's even
referenced in the idea of a daemon
in
computers it's like the magician's
familiar
it's
this little trainable or learning entity
that
is able to carry things out
according to the will of the magician
in a semi-autonomous way
it's not just computers though we've
automated some tasks for us
through the years through the ways of
like even just with running water like
we you know that's an automated task
that used to be a big portion of your
daily life as a human like going to find
water
um
and i mean washing machines dishwashers
we've all all the things i mean we've
been automating life for forever so now
it's just becoming more sophisticated
now perhaps we're automating our
cognitive life like with gpt3 i think
that that's like a
a different kind of
yes we're it's um approaching automation
at the semantic and linguistic level
whereas previously it could be like at
the task the physical task performance
level could be offsourced or uploaded in
a sense
this is like
rapidly
rising
in its
cognitive complexity
[Music]
like a typewriter is a mere active
entity it's part of extended cognition
type type type type type but unless it
gets jammed one is not going to be too
surprised by how it performs
um and that's like the famous turing
quote from back in the day and someone
said like um how can it have
intelligence or um if it can't give a
surprising answer and uh and then
turning said something like
computers surprised me every day
so is that going to be your measure how
surprised you are
um
let's see
i want to look at the partition
question that dave raised and also the
earlier question from dave when he wrote
about the result of cognitive offloading
it was um it was more about cognitive
uploading he clarified in the chat
but i was thinking
yeah i was thinking about the partition
too like when i was talking about i
meant to say partition in there because
it's a temporal partition going from
this generation to the next or is it
like a cognitive or like a
organismal partition between like me and
you or me and my daughter or this group
in that group
the partition is the fuzziness of the
partition always makes it interesting
okay what else let's let's that's it
let's read his question
so in some papers
other than this one
so here's the niche of papers citing
each other
we're in an adjacent regime of an
attention but it's it's relevant
the point comes up and this comes up
indeed in discussion
anatomical or mechanical blankets
so at the cellular level this would be
like the lipid bilayer cell membrane at
the organismal level this would be like
the epithelial so anatomical gross or
micro
mechanical blankets
sometimes
coincide with functional psychological
blankets and sometimes not
so
two brain regions
that are separated but have an interface
it might be the case that their function
could be ascribed with a certain
partition
that reflected the partitioning
topologically of the anatomical
components or it could totally not be
that way so sometimes
anatomical mechanical blankets coincide
with functional psychological blankets
and sometimes not
insert all the asterisks that we've ever
had about realism and instrumentalism
but just we're going to plunge ahead
what is the relation
among
that distinction
between the two kinds of blanketing
this one more of a
embodied enacted realist flavor
and this one more of a
functionalist
flavor
so what is the relation among a b and c
here so what is
it's a relation of relation of relations
as per usual
we're relating a b and c
where
a
is the relationship between these kinds
of blankets
b
is the hierarchical and hierarchical
nesting of blankets
and c is the relations
between or among niches
and the particles that upload
functionality to those niches
what do you think blue about when they
say that the answer is in the question
like the way that the question is asked
contains the seeds of an answer
what do you think about that
um i mean
are you talking about like
how i would
you know
cognitive offload information as an
undergraduate just because i could tell
by the way that the question was asked
yeah like i think i did that
um like i think i looked for i looked
for the answer in the question quite
often as long as it's a multiple choice
question that was pretty simple or if it
wasn't there was often somewhere else in
the test in a different question so like
okay so yeah i did that um
but i think here
there's definitely some
answering here happening like that
distinction what is that like i hate
those i hate those words i hate i hate
those words as i use like a the similar
like referential what is the name of
like the part the part of speech that it
is this that those these
you know those those words
words that are um
oh it's an article
it's an article because the pronoun is
like he she it so it's the articles so
the articles really bother me i think
that
um that distinction the distinction
between anatomical and mechanical
blankets or the functional psychological
blankets yes i'll write it out i believe
it's the distinction between anatomical
mechanical
and functional psychological
those so it should be a plural article
that's what was throwing me
um
yeah anyway the nesting of blankets is
always something like i am down to talk
about but but here
i don't know
does the the does the distinction need
to be drawn if you're talking about
nesting of blankets
how can you
make distinctions between different
types of blankets i don't know
maybe that's just me
we what do you think we explored some
aspects of it
when
[Music]
you mention the multi-scale
approach where like we can think of
nesting
as the bigger nested system whether it
hosts only one
active entity within it or multiple
laterally interacting entities
the bigger nesting
so putting a aside for now
the bigger nested system
can be seen of as the niche for the
subunit or subunits inside of it
and so
for sure
this
b and c can be connected
because
the
nested system
its niche its environment what its
actions are going into and what it is
getting sense information from
is the niche and that is like the larger
nested system
now how do nested systems
using that as a shorthand for both b and
c
connect to this
structural and functional perspective
on systems
are nested systems when we talk about
nested systems
in what ways
can be yes and is it a
structural
nesting like the word is inside the
sentence inside of the paragraph
or in what ways is it a
functional
nesting
where
the functional nesting of concepts
doesn't necessarily have to follow from
the nesting of like sentences on the
page
i think that's a very
challenging but important question and
then also when you mentioned like the
undergrad example um and we've been
talking a lot about test taking right
here
it made me think about how in undergrad
or potentially even earlier yes it was
possible to like kind of reverse
engineer and so like the answer is in
the seeds of the question is kind of
like a game to play where you're just
trying to maximize your score on some
test
but then you get rugged in grad school
where it is still true that the question
that you're asking to nature to the
system
contains the seeds of the answer like
you're only going to get the data for
your experiment
of the kind that you measure on the
number that you actually measure it from
where the conditions that you set them
up to be in
but
if one tries to p hack nature
or if one tries to do that sort of
undergrad i'm going to maximize i mean
these two groups must be different right
so i'm going to try to
measure them with a thumb on the scale
so that they come out to be different
that becomes
tantamount to basically non-rigorous
non-reproducible science
so it just shows i think also to
dean's
continued themes
of like in the lab in the classroom and
then out
so
the highest test score
is not necessarily the highest performer
on that
out in the wild that's towards the
application side
nor necessarily the best teacher
as we've been discussing and so it's
sort of like there's like learning and
development and sometimes it feeds back
on itself with teaching
and other times it just plunges ahead
with application
to all these different
phenomena of learning teaching and
applying
do those all
use the same
partitioning
are they featuring or highlighting their
regime of attention on different parts
of the partitioning
so
that's like where i can't ever close my
instrumentalist eye
it is in the
partition
point because the partition is just
wherever you put it
yes it's how you see it slash model it
unless one specifically wants to
make claims about
realism
i see right i mean
but even if you want like when i
investigate realist claims like if i
look for a partition like what
partitions me from the rest of the world
it's like my skin right so like my skin
is the the boundary it's the markov
blanket that holds me in and the world
out but like i'm losing pieces of my
skin every day it gets cut open and so
so then am i is my partition broken or
like you know am i somehow not the same
person i don't know so for me finding
this like boundary that's like solid and
never changes is not doesn't sit right
so that's why like i always have to
remind myself
it's an instrument so i can never ever
lose my instrumentalist perspective and
get into full realism when i think about
the blanket
so
um it's it's non non-separability it's
you know this is goes back to the
quantum chris fields
you know we're non-separable
fun
times so i think in uh
dot two
let's just write a few notes down and
then close out
so i think in dot two we can
look over some formalisms and see how
the quake equation is connected
we can think about what we discussed
about the fastest time scale is
perception
action
learning
teaching
applying
etc
how do these different modes of
engagement with extended active
inference systems
differ
or what about finding
discovering
so like when you're not taught you know
when you don't know the path and you
find the
tr the stack of rocks
how do we go from a verb ending in ing
to an appropriate
or useful active model
how do we go from
negotiating
trusting
discomforting
community to
get communicating to
the right
graphical structure of a generative
model that we can use in our standard
academic routines
as patiently reminded we all are
by carl on those points
very cool
okay
fun times thanks a lot dean for
joining
yeah dean hope you feel better yep
absolutely and blue thanks a ton was um
fun discussion thanks everybody who's in
the live chat dave and tucker and
stephen and
everybody is welcome to join us next
week for
41.2
on 13th
and in the papers beyond so thank you
all see you later
peace bye
you